Hi.
This is Jessica Smith with Blands Nursery in North Jordan, Utah.
Today we're talking about peonies.
Either pronounced peony or peony, depending on what part of the country you're from.
They are an old time favorite in old fashioned gardens with huge blooms in the springtime and then after they're done blooming, it makes a nice little green shrub in any type of a flower bed or a shrub bed.
There are two types of peonies.
The herbaceous types that die down to the ground each year and then emerge with new leaves each year, or the tree types.
The tree types are a woody type of a plant, more like a flowering shrub.
Both of them produce those huge plants in the spring.
When planting peonies, make sure you prepare the soil with some nice, organic matter.
Now peonies, if you're planting bare root, you'll want to make sure that you plant the herbaceous types at least two inches below the soil level and the tree types at least four inches below the soil level.
If you plant a peony too deep, it actually will not bloom for you.
And also if you're using a bare root type or one that somebody's giving you off one that they've just divided remember, it may take some time for it to reestablish, so it'll be a while before it blooms.
Peonies like a full, sunny location.
One of the best things that you can do for your peonies is actually give them support.
They're so top heavy that those big blooms will actually make them fall over.
So put a peony cage around them.
Put it down around the plant early enough in the spring so as the plant grows up, it'll grow through it.